Finding aid to the Helen Gurley Brown papers SSC.MS.00022
Sophia Smith Collection
Helen Gurley Brown papers
1938-2012
1961-1990
Sophia Smith Collection
Brown, Helen Gurley
SSC.MS.00022
22.5 linear feet (47 containers)
Helen Gurley Brown was editor of Cosmopolitan magazine, advertising copywriter, journalist, and author. The bulk of the material provides a comprehensive picture of Brown's intertwined personal and professional lives. Materials include speeches and scripts, writings, audiovisual material, and memorabilia, as well as records from Cosmopolitan. A large selection of photographs include images of celebrity friends. There is extensive correspondence from celebrities, publishers, fans, and others. Correspondents include Edward Koch, Letty Cottin Pogrebin, and Barbara Walters.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use with following restrictions on access: new, unprocessed accessions and a small amount of correspondence are closed. Three pieces of correspondence with Liz Smith are closed to research until the year 2060 -- in SSC Closed Materials boxes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Helen Gurley Brown donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection beginning in 1972.
Additional Formats
Selections of audiotapes from this collection have been digitized and are available to view online (on Smith campus only).
Arrangement
This collection is organized into six series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
II. CORRESPONDENCE
III. SPEECHES AND APPEARANCES
IV. WRITINGS
V. COSMOPOLITAN
VI. OVERSIZE MATERIALS
Biographical / Historical
Author and magazine editor Helen Gurley Brown was born in Green Forest, Arkansas on 18 February 1922 to Ira and Cleo (Sisco) Gurley, both schoolteachers. Though the family was poor, Cleo quit teaching to rear her two daughters. In Helen's early childhood, the Gurleys moved to Little Rock when Ira was elected to the state legislature. He was killed in an elevator accident when Helen was ten. Cleo struggled to support her children in depression-era Arkansas, first moving back with family in the Ozark region, and then taking Helen and her older sister Mary to Los Angeles in the late 1930s. In Los Angeles, Mary contracted polio, which strained the Gurley's already grim financial condition. Despite hardship, Helen excelled socially and academically. She was active in leadership positions in several high school clubs and graduated class valedictorian.
Helen Gurley spent a year at the Texas State College for Women and then returned to Los Angeles to put herself through Woodbury Business College. Cleo and Mary moved back to Arkansas but remained dependent on Helen's financial support, a situation which continued for the remainder of their lives. Helen graduated from Woodbury with a business degree in 1941 and took on a succession of secretarial jobs. The seventeenth job, at the advertising agency Foote, Cone, and Belding, was pivotal to Helen's future success.
Helen Gurley worked as executive secretary to Don Belding. During this time, she won a Glamour magazine contest for "Girls of Taste" that awarded her a vacation and a wardrobe. She had an active dating life, including a romance with prizefighter Jack Dempsey. Gurley's hard work captured the attention of her boss, and at the suggestion of his wife, Don Belding experimented, allowing Helen to write advertising copy. She succeeded at the task, and moved from secretarial work to copywriting. She wrote ads for several accounts, won prizes for her copy, and by the late 1950s had become the best-paid female copywriter on the West Coast.
In 1959, at the age of 37, Helen found a marriage partner in David Brown, a magazine and book editor who would become a film executive at the Twentieth Century Fox Studios, and later an independent producer. He was also an uncredited partner behind many of Helen's projects. After she found her advertising career stagnating at Foote, Cone, and Belding and then the Kenyon and Eckhardt Agency, it was David who encouraged her to write a book about her life as a single woman. The result, Sex and the Single Girl (1962), captured a zeitgeist of the early 1960s.
Bernard Geis Associates, a maverick publishing house, found great success with Brown's book, a guide to living single "in superlative style." It later published the wildly successful potboilers of Jacqueline Susann. Sex and the Single Girl, an advice manual that exhorted women to remain single and find fulfillment in an occupation and non-marital relationships with men, sparked national controversy and remained on the best-seller lists for months. Helen Gurley Brown made frequent personal, television, and radio appearances to promote the book. Rights to the title were sold to Warner Brothers at the highest price then ever paid for a non-fiction title. The film, Sex and the Single Girl (1964), starred Natalie Wood (as Helen Gurley Brown) and Tony Curtis.
Following the success of Sex and the Single Girl, David Brown and Bernard Geis Associates marketed Helen in a variety of enterprises. She wrote a syndicated newspaper advice column, recorded phonograph albums and radio spots, and wrote prodigiously. Her next book, Sex and the Office (1964), a racier advice manual and expose of a sex-filled world of secretaries, sold disappointingly in comparison to Sex and the Single Girl.
The Browns submitted proposals for a variety of works to keep up the momentum of Helen's popularity following Sex and the Single Girl: plays, television shows, other books, and magazines. Their proposal for a magazine for single women ("Femme") drew the interest of the Hearst magazine corporation. Though they did not want to start a new magazine for Brown, they made a trial agreement for her to try her format at their failing general interest magazine, Cosmopolitan. Brown officially became editor of Cosmopolitan in July 1965, and she brought dramatic changes to the first issue.
Brown converted the conservative Cosmopolitan to a female counterpart of Hugh Hefner's iconic Playboy magazine. She featured sexy cover models, controversial subject matter, and a hip sensibility that garnered a large audience quickly. While editing Cosmopolitan, Helen Gurley Brown authored The Single Girl's Cookbook (1969) and Sex and the New Single Girl (1971), continued to be a guest on many TV shows, and became one of Hearst's biggest success stories. Meanwhile, David Brown, along with partner Richard Zanuck, produced many successful films, including The Sting, Jaws, Cocoon, Deep Impact, and Chocolat.
In 1983 Helen wrote the best-seller Having it All, an advice manual and memoir in the style of Sex and the Single Girl. In the 1980s, she also had television stints as a regular on Good Morning America, a short-lived syndicated show A View from Cosmo, and was a guest on talk shows. She continued to edit the highly successful Cosmopolitan, which had by the 1980s grown to 300 pages, of which a hundred were highly lucrative advertisements. She oversaw expansion of the Cosmopolitan franchise into numerous international editions. In 1993 she wrote The Late Show, an advice manual and memoir about growing older. She published a writing guide, The Writer's Rules, in 1999, and in 2000 wrote her definitive memoir, I'm Wild Again.
Brown's career was often marked by controversy. Sex and the Single Girl, a celebration of independent womanhood published a year before Betty Friedan's The Feminine Mystique, sparked much dispute about women's place in pre-women's movement popular culture. In a literary world that had only recently seen the lessening of stringent restrictions on the portrayal of sex, Brown's emphasis on sex drew much opposition from conservative critics. However, by the late 1960s, she and her vision of adamantly man-crazy womanhood drew opposition from non-conservatives as well. The incipient women's movement targeted Brown's limited vision of liberation. Feminists criticized the sex-object "Cosmo Girl" and envisioned a mass media that reflected a greater range of possibilities for women than the pink collar, man-obsessed vision of Cosmopolitan. Brown's idiosyncratic notions of liberation and sexual freedom raised controversy in later years as well. In the 1990s, her dismissal of sexual harassment as a significant workplace problem and her indifference to the risk of AIDS for heterosexual women drew great wrath again from feminists. Brown nonetheless identified herself and her magazine as unfailingly feminist. She worked on behalf of the National Abortion Rights Action League in support of abortion rights and supported other feminist organizations and causes.
While Brown was frequently the target of criticism, in the last years of her life she also accumulated accolades. Her work at Cosmopolitan was recognized through her election to the Publishing Hall of Fame and a Henry Johnson Fisher Award. She was declared a New York City landmark, being a familiar presence on New York City busses heading from her Central Park West apartment to the Cosmopolitan office. Her admirers and friends included gossip columnist Liz Smith, television journalist Barbara Walters, mogul Malcolm Forbes, and New York Mayor Ed Koch.
In 1997 Brown gave up her editorship of Cosmopolitan to become editor-in-chief of international editions of the magazine. Far from a retiree, she remained a workaholic in her new job, enjoyed travel with David, who continued to produce hit films until his death in 2010, and still voiced "outrageous" opinions that made her a frequent presence in newspapers and magazines. In early 2012 she established the David and Helen Gurley Brown Institute for Media Innovation, donating $30 million dollars to collaborating institutions, Columbia University Graduate School of Journalism and Stanford School of Engineering. Helen Gurley Brown died in a Manhattan hospital on 13 August 2012.
Scope and Contents
Types of material in this collection include personal and professional correspondence, published and unpublished writings, personal records and memorabilia, printed materials, photographs, biographical materials, an audiotaped interview, videotapes, phonograph albums, scrapbooks, and posters.
Some material pertaining primarily to David Brown can be found in SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS and SERIES IV. WRITINGS. Since he collaborated with Helen on many of her projects, his work is interspersed throughout her papers. Helen Gurley Brown has been a pivotal figure in the magazine world in the second half of the twentieth century, and her papers give an insider's look into the Hearst organization, one of the most powerful media organizations of this century, and the publishing industry in general. The papers also address topics well beyond the world of magazines. Her work as an advertising copywriter at a time when women were not expected to work outside of the home certainly deserves consideration, and her call for "liberation" of the single woman was among the first. Brown's rags to riches career was unusual at a time when most women still did not work outside the home. Her experience of moving from pink-collar clerical worker to wealthy doyenne of the mass media was unique. She helped shape the popular culture of the 1960s and beyond. Sex and the Single Girl ushered in a spate of "Sex and the..." imitators but also launched a cultural dialogue on the question of the unmarried, sexually active, employed woman. The look of Cosmopolitan, which was conveyed on the signature covers photographed by Francesco Scavullo and the racy cover blurbs, defined young women's magazines for much of the second half of the twentieth century. As her career progressed, Brown associated with rich and influential people, who are well-represented in her collection. Additionally, the strong responses, both positive and negative, elicited by Brown's work give a sense of changing and conflicting public opinion on questions of sex, gender, and the media.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies.
Advertising--United States--History--20th century; Celebrities--New York (State)--New York; Journalism--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Periodicals--Publishing--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Sex in mass media--United States--History--20th century; Secretaries--United States--History--Sources; Single women--Sexual behavior--History; Women--Life skills guides; Women executives--United States; Women in advertising--United States--History- 20th century; Women in mass media--United States--History--20th century; Women in the professions--United States--History--20th century; Women editors--United States; New York (N.Y.)--Social life and customs--20th century--Sources; Pogrebin, Letty Cottin--Correspondence; Koch, Ed, 1924- --Correspondence; Reynolds, Burt; Walters, Barbara, 1931- --Correspondence; Taylor, Elizabeth, 1932- --Correspondence; Bennack, Frank A. (Frank Anthony), 1933- --Correspondence; Siegel, Herbert Jay, 1928- --Correspondence; correspondence; photographs; Audiotapes; Videotapes; Writings; clippings; Speeches; Radio scripts; Phonograph records; scrapbooks; Typescripts; Bernard Geis Associates (New York, N.Y.); Cosmopolitan (New York, N.Y.: 1952)--History; Hearst Corporation; Brown, Helen Gurley
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS, 1938-2000
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes material that documents Helen Gurley Brown's personal life and professional accomplishments. There are clippings, appointment books, travel itineraries, awards, and photographs. There is also a file of material from and about David Brown. The many Clippings give a comprehensive picture of the heavy press coverage Brown has received throughout her career. They stretch from her schoolgirl days in Little Rock to the present. The Education material primarily covers Brown's involvement later in life with her alma mater Woodbury College. This series contains miscellaneous Financial and legal material, including a 1946 income tax return; Awards; and a Videotape profile of Brown aired on CNN. The Memorabilia is especially engaging, containing writings and ephemera from her years in Little Rock and those pre-dating Sex and the Single Girl. The Papers contain a large selection of Photographs, some shot by celebrity photographers, and many with celebrity friends.
  - General, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings
    General
    [see also SERIES IV. WRITINGS and SERIES V. COSMOPOLITAN]
    - Print interviews of Brown: correspondence, 1963-2000; undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Books and papers, 1991; undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Family and early life, circa, 1935-59 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Beaux" (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Helen and David Brown (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - David Brown (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Parties and charity events (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Awards and tributes to Brown (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Speeches and appearances (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Apartment and office (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - General (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - General, continued (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Photos of Brown, no text (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Brown quotes within articles not about her, box quotes, etc. (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - Interviews and panels (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Foreign language (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Appointment and address books
    - 1965-70 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
    - 1971-72 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Education (includes correspondence and printed material from Wayne Miller and Woodbury University), 1984-2001 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Foote, Cone, and Belding job evaluation, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Financial and legal materials
    - Correspondence, 1964-89 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Statements, stubs, miscellany, tax return, and Sex and the Single Girl royalty statements, 1946; 1963-69; 1980-85 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Clothes: drawings, measurements, and expenditures, 1966-71; undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Travel itineraries, general, 1966-69; undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    [See also SERIES IV. WRITINGS and SERIES V. COSMOPOLITAN]
  - Awards
    [See also SERIES V. COSMOPOLITAN]
    - Correspondence, 1971-98 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Publicity, invitations, and printed material, 1971-97 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
    - Cosmetic Executive Women's Achiever, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - USO Woman of the Year, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Memorabilia: personal stationary, handmade cards, wedding invitation, and four leaf clover, circa, 1938-39; 1951-52; 1959; 1985; undated (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
  - David Brown: printed material, notes, and testimonial by Helen Brown, 1966; 1972; 1979; 1992; 1995; undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Photographs
    [See also SERIES VI. OVERSIZE MATERIALS]
    - Brown alone, circa, 1930s-99 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
    - Family (includes photos of Helen and David Brown, and mother and sister alone), circa, 1940s-90s (Box 5, Folder 4)
      [For shots of Helen and David Brown with others, see Helen Brown in groups]
    - Helen Brown in groups, circa, 1940s-mid-90s (Box 5, Folder 5-9)
    - Promotional shots of book covers and clippings, 1962-82 (Box 5a, Folder 1-2)
    - Twenty-fifth anniversary party, 1990 (Box 5a, Folder 3)
    - Henry Johnson Fisher Award, 1996 (Box 5a, Folder 4)
    - Brown on Tonight Show, Merv Griffin, Good Morning America, David Brenner, 1967-early 1990s (Box 5a, Folder 5)
    - Not Helen or David Brown, circa, 1950s-70s; undated (Box 5a, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified, circa, 1930s? (Box 5a, Folder 7)
  - Videotape: Helen Gurley Brown: A Profile, CNN, 1998; 2 Cassettes (2 copies) (Box 6, Folder 1)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE, 1939; 1950-2001
  Brown was always a prodigious correspondent. Her correspondence is organized into several subseries. The Individuals subseries is arranged alphabetically by name and includes friends, frequent correspondents, and correspondence more personal than businesslike. Accordingly correspondence can be found here that is related to her work at Cosmopolitan, her writings, speeches and appearances, or other topics located elsewhere in her papers. Correspondence with celebrities is filed in Individuals.
  The next subseries is Thank you and congratulatory notes, mostly from her staff at Cosmopolitan magazine, but also from her household staff and employers at Hearst. This correspondence is mainly of a quotidian nature, but illustrates how Brown, by many accounts a demanding person, earned the respect of her staff and employers.
  Public response and fan mail includes letters from readers of Brown's writings and viewers of her appearances. Some letters are simple requests for autographs, while others provide detailed and moving accounts of how Brown's plan for success helped these generally working-class women find degrees of fulfillment. The extent to which these women embraced Cosmopolitan's message is in sharp contrast to the criticism leveled at the magazine by many conservatives and feminists.
  Correspondence by Subject includes letters generated by Brown's philanthropic work, critiques of magazines other than Cosmopolitan and other Hearst properties, letters from libraries and museums interested in Brown's work, love letters from the 1950s, and correspondence with friends from Little Rock. The bulk of the Subject correspondence involves Editor's perquisites/gifts. These letters reveal Brown's personal interest in clothes and cosmetics. Noted for her thrift, she often used her clout as an editor of a women's magazine to obtain these items wholesale. Manufacturers and designers, eager to have their products highlighted in Cosmopolitan, and others because they were friends, obliged. These letters give no indication that the products were intended for the pages of Cosmopolitan; such correspondence can be found in SERIES V. COSMOPOLITAN. As best as can be determined, the letters here pertain to gifts and perquisites that were for Brown's personal use.
  General correspondence contains letters of a quotidian nature, regarding home repairs and so forth.
  This series contains most of Brown's correspondence, but there is additional correspondence in other series. For example, correspondence generated by the planning and execution of speeches and appearances, with publishers and media figures interested in Helen's writings, and tied explicitly to her work at Cosmopolitan can be found in the relevant series. Correspondence connected to specific projects has been kept with the project whenever possible. An exception to this rule is celebrity correspondence, which has been filed in SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE-Individuals even though it may relate to a specific project. Determining whether or not correspondence should be categorized as professional or personal was one of the biggest challenges of this collection, since Brown's work and personal life were enmeshed. Many of the people with whom she maintained friendships were figures in the media. In general, the correspondence included in SERIES V. COSMOPOLITAN is explicitly related to the production of the magazine. Nonetheless, many of the correspondents in SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE are at least tangentially related to Cosmopolitan.
  - Family
    - Alford, Mary Gurley (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Brown, David: with Helen Brown and third party, includes John Dos Passos, Charles Bluhdorn, John Lindsay, Sammy Cahn, A.M. Rosenthal, Felix Rohatyn, Liz Smith, and Earl Wilson (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
    - Bryan, Cleo (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Individuals
    - A: Floyd Abrams; Michael Abrums; Bella Abzug; Mr. and Mrs. Ed Acker; Mona Ackerman; Cindy Adams;Charles Addams; Jerome Agel; Roger Ailes; Shana Alexander; Woody Allen; Bruce Altman; Carlos Amador; Totty Ames; Cleveland Amory; Judi Anderson; Paul Anderson; Julie Andrews; Walter Annenberg; Myra, John, and Malcolm Appleton; GigiArledge; Lucie Arnaz; Sharon Arnold; Dr. Bob Arnot; Bea Arthur; Joseph Assante; Sherrell Aston and Muffie Potter; Robert Atkins; and Louis Auchincloss (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Ba-Be: Judy Bachrach; F. Lee Bailey; Glenda and Steve Bailey; Marilyn Cantor Baker; Russell Baker; Letitia Baldridge; Larry Baldwin and John Clerc Scott; Lucy Ball; Lawrence Barnett; Bruce Barone; Mary Ellen Berlin Barrett; Warren Beatty; Geoffrey Beene; Charlotte Beers; Don and Alice Belding; Tony Bennett; Polly Bergen; Irving Berlin; H. Jerome Berns; and Robert Bernstein (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Bi-Bl: Jim Bickford; Bennett Bidwell; Elizabeth Jessup Bilheimer; Stephen and Alexandra Mayes Birnbaum; Joey Bishop; Joanne Black; Ruth Blackstone; Harry Blake; Leslie Blanchard; and Charles Bluhdorn (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Bo-Bu: William Bolger; Erma Bombeck; Ray Bradbury; Patricia Salter Bradshaw; James Brady; Jacqueline Brandwynne; Bill Brangham; David Brenner; Marie Brenner; David Brinkley; Tom Brokaw; Bob Brown (love letters from 1940s); Ned Brown; Sam Brown; Tina Brown; Tony Brown; Robert Brownson; Robert Bruce; Karen Bruno; Art Buchwald; William F. Buckley, Jr.; Howard Buffett; Carol Burnett; Barbara Bush; and Red Buttons (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Ca-Ci: Herb Caen; William and Grace Cahan; Sammy and Tita Cahn; Sue Cameron; Rosemary Campbell; Pat Carbine; Pamela Carmichael; Liz Carpenter; Johnny Carson; Amy Carter; Jimmy and Rosalyn Carter; Linda and Arthur Carter; Jill Cassidy; Ray Cave; Dick Cavett; Anne Chamberlain; Chris Chase; Eileen (Elizabeth) and Robert Chen; Henry Christensen, III; Herman Citron; Richard Civita; Roberto Civita; and Victor Civita (Box 7, Folder 1)